The most common way that professionals measure the spread of a data
الطريقة الأكثر شيوعًا التي يقيس بها المحترفون انتشار مجوعة بيانات
set with a single value is with the standard deviation or variance.
ذات قيمة واحدة هي الانحراف المعياري أو المتفاوت.
Here, we will focus on the standard deviation,
هنا، سنركز على الانحراف المعياري،
but we will actually learn how to calculate the variance in the process.
ولكن سنتعلم بالفعل كيفية حساب المتفاوت في العملية.
If you have never heard of these measures before,
إذا لم تسمع مطلقًا بهذه المقاييس من قبل،
this calculation will probably look pretty complex.
فإن هذه العملية الحسابية قد تبدو معقدة للغاية.
When all's said and done with this calculation,
عندما يتم كل شيء باستخدام هذه العملية الحسابية،
the standard deviation will tell us on average
سيخبرنا الانحراف المعياري في المتوسط
how far every point is from the mean of the points.
عن مدى بعد كل نقطة من وسط النقاط.
As a quick mental picture,
كصورة ذهنية سريعة،
imagine we wanted to know how far employees were located from their place of work.
تخيلوا إننا نريد أن نعرف مدى بعد الموظفين الموجودين عن مكان عملهم.
One person might be 15 miles,
يبعد شخص ما 15 ميلًا،
another 35, another only one mile,
وآخر 35 وآخر ميل واحد فقط،
and another might be remote and is 103 miles.
وآخر قد يكون بعيدًا بمسافة قدرها 103 أميال.
We could aggregate all of these distances together to show that
يمكنك تجميع كل هذه المسافات معًا لنوضح أن
the average distance employees are located from their work is 18 miles.
يبلغ متوسط مسافة الموظفين الموجودين من عملهم هو 18 ميلًا.
But now, we want to know how the distance to work varies from one employee to the next.
ولكن الآن، نريد معرفة كيف تتغير المسافة إلى العمل من موظف إلى آخر.
We could use the five number summary as a description.
يمكننا أن نستخدم ملخص الخمس أعداد كإحصائية وصفية.
But if we wanted just one number to talk about the spread,
ولكن إذا أردت رقم واحد فقط للتحدث عن الانتشار،
we'd probably choose the standard deviation.
ربما سنختار الانحراف المعياري.
The standard deviation is on average how much each observation varies from the mean.
الانحراف المعياري هو في المتوسط، مدى تفاوت كل ملاحظة من الوسط.
For this example this is,
على سبيل المثال هذا هو،
how much on average the distance each person is from
كيف تختلف في المتوسط مسافة كل فرد من مكان عمله
work differs from the average distance all of them are from work.
عن متوسط المسافة لهم جميعًا من مكان العمل.
So, this one is three miles farther from work than the average
لذا، هذا أبعد من العمل بثلاثة أميال عن المعدل
while this individual is four miles closer to work than the average.
بينما هذا الفرد أقرب للعمل بأربعة أميال عن المعدل.
The standard deviation is how far on
الانحراف المعياري هو مدى بعد الموظفين في المتوسط
average are individuals located from this mean distance.
عن المسافة الوسط.
So, it is like the average of all of these distances.
لذا، فهو بمثابة متوسط لكل هذه المسافات.
We will take a closer look at this but hopefully this gives you
سنلقي نظرة عن قرب على هذا ولكن نأمل أن يعطيك هذا
a strong conceptual understanding of what we'll be calculating in the next sections.
فهم مفاهيمي قوي لما سنقوم بحسابه في الأقسام القادمة.